[MUSIC]
[開放科學]
In this lecture we talk
about open science.
最後一講來談開放科學
We see in recent years that the scientific
community is moving towards more
近年，學界持續開放知識生產流程
的所有環節，讓科學活動更透明
transparency opening up all aspect
of the scientific enterprise.
近年，學界持續開放科學知識生產流程
的所有環節，讓科學活動更透明
We'll discuss what's happening and
這一講會談正在進行的活動
wether you want to join into
this open science movements.
還有提供你加入開放科學運動的建議-
So open science can be divided to,
maybe six different aspecs.
開放科學大致可分成六個面向
(註：https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science)
You have open access to publications,
data,
有出版品的開放檢索、研究資料的開放取用
materials that are used in scientific
research, to peer review process,
研究材料的開放取用
同儕審查程序的透明化
educational resources and
open source software.
公開的教育資源以及開源軟體
Let's talk about all of these in term.
以下讓我逐項介紹
First, open access to
the scientific output.
首先談科學成果的開放檢索
It might sound like it's a good idea
that whenever a taxpayer pays for
現代科學研究主要來自人民納稅的國家經費補助
所有納稅人都能檢索研究成果是合理的主張
scientific research, this taxpayer
also has access to the publications
現代科學研究主要來自人民納稅的國家經費補助
所有納稅人都能檢索研究成果是合理的主張
that come out of this research.
現代科學研究主要來自人民納稅的國家經費補助
所有納稅人都能檢索研究成果是合理的主張
Regrettably at the moment this is not yet
the case.
很可惜目前還未能達成
If someone wants to read
the scientific article
想要閱讀科學論文的讀者
here she has to pay to
get access this article.
必須付費購買檢索權限
This is now an ideal situation and
everybody agrees.
全面開放還是多數人希望達成的理想境界
We see a move towards open access
現在有一些開放模式提供人們免費檢索科學文獻
providing people with access to
the scientific literature without paying.
現在有一些開放模式提供人們免費檢索科學文獻
There are different models to achieve
this one is called Gold Open Access.
其中一種稱為付費式開放檢索
(Gold Open Access)
In this case the researcher or
這種模式由研究者本人或任職的大學付檢索費
the university the researcher works for
have payed to provide access.
這種模式由研究者本人或任職的大學付檢索費
Another option is Green Open Access.
另一種稱為自由式開放檢索
(Green Open Access)
Here the scientific output is still
hidden behind what's known as a paywall.
這種模式還是需要付出一些費用
But a version of the publication,
typically just the Word document,
不過任何人都可以上網閱覽通常是Word格式的文獻手稿
is available for
anyone who wants to read it online.
不過任何人都可以上網閱覽通常是Word格式的文獻手稿
Nowadays we even have less legal
solutions to this problem.
現在還有一種不完全合法的開放檢索管道
There's a website Sci-Hub which provides
access to all the scientific literature
這是由Sci-Hub網站提供的全球科學文獻檢索服務
without having to pay but of course this
is completely illegal at the moment.
Sci-Hub雖不收費但是目前未完全合法
That such a service exists shows that
there's a big problem at the moment.
Sci-Hub的存在顯現達到完全的開放檢索還有問題要克服
And I think that in a couple of years
we'll see a big move towards open access
我認為幾年之內開放檢索會有重大進展
and, hopefully,
而且希望任何有興趣科學研究的個人都能自由檢索科學文獻
making scientific literature available
to anybody who's interested in it.
而且希望任何有興趣科學研究的個人都能自由檢索科學文獻
If you publish a scientific article,
you can see whether you're
若你是科學論文的作者，你可以查詢接受出版的期刊是否允許分享己接受或待出版的手稿
actually allowed to share a pre-print or
a post print to show the word document
若你是科學論文的作者，你可以查詢接受出版的期刊是否允許分享己接受或待出版的手稿
that you submitted to the journal
before publication on a website.
若你是科學論文的作者，你可以查詢接受出版的期刊是否允許分享己接受或待出版的手稿
So you can share this version for
anybody to read.
這類論文格式你可以自行決定分享的方式
So this is green open access model.
所以這是一種自由式開放檢索
(例:academica.edu, researchgate)
So, if you visit this website SHERPA/ROMEO
只要在SHERPA/ROMEO網站查詢
you can see whether you're allowed
to share your scientific output.
就能得知出版文章的期刊有無允許你分享
And this is always a smart thing to do.
這是現在最好的公開模式
Research shows that people who put
this free available versions online
研究者以合法途徑於網路免費分享人人可取用的格式，也能提高研究成果的被引用次數
the legal way get more citations
in their scientific research.
研究者以合法途徑於網路免費分享人人可取用的格式，也能提高研究成果的被引用次數
So this is nice,
可說是兩全其美
people can read it and they'll cite it
more as long as you make it available.
只要能持續分享，人人都能閱讀你的文章並引用之
The second point is sharing
data after publication.
接著談出版論文後的資料分享
When you do this science
becomes more reproducible.
你可以讓你的科學成果更容易被重製
People can take your data and they can
rerun the analysis that you report.
人人都能拿你的資料重新驗證報告中的分析結果
They can even try out different analysis
if they are interested in doing this.
其它人也能嘗試用其它方法分析你的資料-
Data storage itself is not
organized through laws,
資料的儲存沒有任何法律規範
there's no law that says that you have
to store your data somewhere, but
沒有那條法規律定資料存放位置
it's regulated through regulations.
不過通常有公約規範
They're very often,
scientific institutions such as
許多科學機構像是荷蘭大學協會(VSNU)有頒布指導原則
(有意留學荷蘭的同學留意屬於VSNU的大學)
the Dutch Association for universities in
the Netherlands that have guidelines and
許多科學機構像是荷蘭大學協會(VSNU)有頒布指導原則
(有意留學荷蘭的同學留意屬於VSNU的大學)
ask researchers to for
example store their data for 10 years.
要求各校研究者要保存資料至少十年
(有意留學荷蘭的同學留意屬於VSNU的大學)
Now if you collect scientific data and
you publish it, you are require
像我收集的資料在發表論文之後，就要從出版日期開始保存至少十年
to make this data available until at
least 10 years after publication.
像我收集的資料在發表論文之後，就要從出版日期開始保存至少十年-
So data should be made
available upon request.
只要有需求就要保持資料可被取用
When other people in
the scientific community ask for
只要有其它研究者向你索取資料，你應該在起碼合法範圍內與人分享
your data, you should share this at
least whenever it's legally possible.
只要有其它研究者向你索取資料，你應該在起碼合法範圍內與人分享
Now if your department
has no central rules for
如果你任職的單位沒有訂研究資料儲存的規則，就是你個人要付起的責任
data storage, then data storage
is your own responsibility.
如果你任職的單位沒有訂研究資料儲存的規則，就是你個人要付起的責任
Don't store your data on the hard drive
of a single laptop or even worse,
千萬不要把研究資料存在筆記型電腦的硬碟或隨身碟之中
on a USB stick.
The data might just disappear.
因為硬碟有可能損壞
The hard drive might crash and
the data is gone.
導致資料遺失
So it's your responsibility
to make sure that in five,
你的個人責任是維持至少五、六年之內，其它人都能檢索你收集的資料
six years from now people can still have
access to the data that you collected.
你的個人責任是維持至少五,六年之內，其它人都能檢索你收集的資料
Often when you analyze data, you will also
be able to provide an analysis script.
提供資料之外，最好也提供分析資料的程式碼腳本
When you do this,
我建議在程式碼中
try to add comments to whatever
code you use to analyze your data.
加上附註說明每一行進行的分析程序
This is not just useful for other
people but it will also be useful for
這不但有助其他人理解，你自已也能容易回憶這時做過的事情
yourself in the future so that you can
understand your own code more easily.
這不但有助其他人理解，你自已也能容易回憶這時做過的事情
If you create a data file,
give names to the data.
還有給予每個資料欄位合適命名
Provide useful names that
people can understand.
欄位命名能幫助他人了解資料內容
Again this is useful for other people
who want to look at your data later, but
與程式碼註解相同，這能幫助他人理解你的資料
it is also useful if you want to look
at your own data in a couple of years.
你自已將來有天重新查閱時也容易整理
Ideally, when you publish
a scientific article,
原則上，一篇論文出版之後
you will provide the raw data,
the analytic data and the results.
需要提供原始資料(raw data)，分析資料(analytic data)與結果圖表
The raw data is the data as you
collect it with whatever software or
原始資料來自你使用的資料收集軟體或問卷
whatever questionnaires you use.
Then you can typically use
some sort of analysis script
接著會用某種分析腳本將原始資料轉換成分析資料
that transform the raw data
into the analytic data.
接著會用某種分析腳本將原始資料轉換成分析資料
This includes removing outliers or
dealing with missing data.
這個過程包括去掉極端值或處理遺漏值
And it might also include calculating
averages from questionnaires.
也許還有計算幾組平均值
When you have the analytic data then
you have the second set of goal that
有了分析資料，接下來就要製作放在論文結果一節的圖表
creates the results section as you write
it down in your scientific article.
有了分析資料，接下來就要製作放在論文結果一節的圖表
And you might even be able to provide
additional quote from these results that
通常會在圖表旁邊提供附加說明，圖表的元素表示那些資料
lead to figures that you publish in the
article, or tables that you have produced.
通常會在圖表旁邊提供附加說明，圖表的元素表示那些資料
So in the ideal situation, the data
that you share goes from the raw data to
最理想的狀況是你能提供從原始資料，轉換成分析資料，最後形成圖表元素的一切
the analytic data to the results and then
directly to the figures and the tables.
最理想的狀況是你能提供從原始資料，轉換成分析資料，最後形成圖表元素的一切
So this would create a completely
reproducible result section.
如此就是可再製的研究結果-
(延伸:http://danielmarcelino.github.io/blog/2016/reproducible-research.html)
There are some journals that require
all authors to make all data underlying
有些期刊要求投稿者公開論文裡提及的所有資料
the findings described in their manuscript
fully available without restriction,
有些期刊要求投稿者公開論文裡提及的所有資料
with very rare exceptions.
除了極少的例外狀況
PLOS is one of the journals
that does this.
PLOS是這類期刊之一
You might have data that's
really too sensitive to share.
也許有時一些資料比較敏感不宜公開
But in most situations the expectation is
that whenever someone in the scientific
但多數情況是有同行研究者索取資料，你有義務完整提供
community asks for your data,
you'll make it fully available.
但多數情況是有同行研究者索取資料，你有義務完整提供
So it's useful to prepare a data file that
can be easily shared with other people
因此投稿時準備好可分享的研究資料是很有用的習慣
when you submit your scientific
findings for publication.
因此投稿時準備好可分享的研究資料是很有用的習慣-
Many science funders now require what's
known as a data management plan.
許多研究經費補助單位開始要求提出資料管理計畫
(台灣的科技部推給各IRB?)
Whenever they fund scientific research,
they expect that the researcher that
補助者期望研究者展示如何在約定年限內(5~10年）儲存資料的方式
performs this research has some idea
of how the data will be stored for
補助者期望研究者展示如何在約定年限內(5~10年）儲存資料的方式
the foreseeable future.
There are all sorts of technological
solutions nowadays to store data.
今天有許多提供儲存各式資料的雲端服務
Because we have the Internet,
we can share data in the cloud.
這些平台讓我們能透過網路分析資料
And there are all sorts of services
that allow you to upload data files and
這張投影片列舉的平台都能讓你上傳及分享研究資料
share them with other people.
這張投影片列舉的平台都能讓你上傳及分享研究資料-
From data we can also move
on to sharing materials.
除了資料我們也可以分享研究材料
If you've published something and you
share all the materials that you used in
將原始論文中的研究材料公開更能有效促進科學知識進步
your original research, this will
make science much more efficient.
將原始論文中的研究材料公開更能有效促進科學知識進步
Other people can use the same materials
either to try to replicate your result or
其它人能用同樣的材料進行再現研究(見本週第一講)
to build on it and
to test new theoretical prediction.
也能用設計新研究測試新理論-
The Open Science Framework is a free
servers that allows researchers to share
開放科學平台(osf.io)是提供研究同伴間分享研究材料與資料的免費雲端服務
whatever they want, materials but
also data with fellow scientists or
開放科學平台(osf.io)是提供研究同伴間分享研究材料與資料的免費雲端服務
anybody who wants access to it.
任何人都能取用公開的檔案
On the right you see a list of
files that we've share to relate it
投影片右邊是我的某份已出版研究的材料清單
to a research project that we published.
You can see that we share
the questionnaire that we use so
如果你想進行有關的研究
other people can use the same
questionnaire if they want.
你可以直接下載這份研究使用的問卷
But we also share some sound files
that were used in this studies.
此外也分享這項研究使用的語音檔案
Of course in the publication we tried to
described the content of the sound files,
雖然內容很複雜，我在論文中已儘可能描述語音內容
but that's very difficult.
And by just giving people access to the
sound files that we used, we can make it
提供語音檔案能讓其它人更容易了解我們的研究方法
as easy as possible for other people
to understand what we did exactly and
提供語音檔案能讓其它人更容易了解我們的研究方法
to build on this line of
research if they want to.
也能幫助之後的研究者建立研究進程-
Nowadays we're trying to reward
these kind of practices.
現在已有獎勵這些公開行為的措施
One example of a reward
program is the use of badges.
其中一項是頒發獎章
Whenever you publish research,
只要你成功發表的研究論文
where you make data openly available,
materials openly available or
有做到開放資料、開放研究材料
where you have pre-registered your
hypothesis before collecting the data.
或者收集資料前完成註冊
This will be clearly marked.
你的論文就會獲得這些獎章
Now it might sound a little bit
like you're back in kindergarten.
這看起來有點像幼稚園園長的管理方法
Whenever you perform good behavior you get
a sticker, but making these good behaviors
小朋友表現好就給一支棒棒糖，不過這樣的方式是讓開放科學的重要性能清楚呈現於世人之前
clearly visible is an important
aspect of promoting open science
小朋友表現好就給一支棒棒糖，不過這樣的方式是讓開放科學的重要性能清楚呈現於世人之前-
Another aspect of open science is
opening the peer review process.
開放的同儕審查是開放科學的另一項重點
The goal of this is to make
science more transparent.
目的是讓科學更透明
We can see that some journals are now not
just publishing their research itself,
例如這本期刊不只刊出接受的研究論文
they also provide access
to the peer review history.
也提供讀者查閱論文的審查紀錄
When an article is submitted for
作者投出一篇文章後，通常有數位審查者評估論文品質
publication, peers evaluate
the quality of the article.
作者投出一篇文章後，通常有數位審查者評估論文品質
By giving access to the peer review
history, you can see the communication
從審查紀錄之中可以看到論文被正式接受之前審查者的意見
between peers before the final
version of the article was published.
從審查紀錄之中可以看到論文被正式接受之前審查者的意見
This gives more transparency
to the Peer Review Process.
如此能讓同儕審查程序更透明
A final aspect that I want to mention
is the use of open source software.
最後一項是開源軟體的使用
The goal of using open source
software is making data and
使用開源軟體能讓其它人不需購買商用軟體
就能取用研究資料與分析程序
analyses more available,
more accessible to people that
使用開源軟體能讓其它人不需購買商用軟體
就能取用研究資料與分析程序
might not be able to buy
commercially available software.
使用開源軟體能讓其它人不需購買商用軟體
就能取用研究資料與分析程序-
For example in this course, we rely on R.
例如本課程大量使用的R語言
Free statistical software that anybody
with access to a computer can download.
就是只要能使用電腦上網的使用者都能下載的軟體
If we would use commercially
available statistical tools,
如果使用商用統計軟體(如SPSS,Matlab)
then we would rely on people to be able to
buy the software before they can follow
必須指望使用者能在做作業或分析資料前能買到這些軟體
along with assignments or
sometimes with analyzing data.
必須指望使用者能在做作業或分析資料前能買到這些軟體
And this is something we want to prevent.
這是設計研究時必須避免的
We want to make the data as accessible as
possible to as many people as possible.
研究的資料要讓越多人容易取用越好-
Another thing to keep in mind,
in terms of transparency,
另外讓科學知識更透明的重點是揭露利益衝突(conflicts of inteest)
is to disclose conflicts of interest.
另外讓科學知識更透明的重點是揭露利益衝突(conflicts of interest)
When personal interests potentially
compromise scientific objectivity,
當個人利益與科學客觀性有抵觸時
you're supposed to disclose this for
example, when you were refueling(reviewing) articles
像是你正在審查或發表與個人有關文章
or when you're publishing
scientific articles yourself.
都要坦白涉及的利益關係
The example of this where conflicts of
interest we're not this closed comes from
一個著名的例子是菸草工業試圖干涉研究者，發表支持「吸煙不一定會致癌」的研究結果
the tobacco industry which try to cast
doubt on smoking causing cancer by making
一個著名的例子是菸草工業試圖干涉研究者，發表支持「吸煙不一定會致癌」的研究結果
statements such as there is no conclusive
proof that smoking causes cancer.
一個著名的例子是菸草工業試圖干涉研究者，發表支持「吸煙不一定會致癌」的研究結果
Now of course this first
of all shows they were not
菸草公司的意圖並不是基於科學哲學的理由
really well first in
philosophy of science.
菸草公司的意圖並不是基於科學哲學的理由
We can never have conclusive
proof of anything.
試圖證明科學永遠不能證明任何事實
Well there was overwhelming support for
今天已有成千上萬的研究結果支持吸煙與癌症的關係
the idea that there was a relationship
between smoking and cancer.
今天已有成千上萬的研究結果支持吸煙與癌症的關係
Of course, some researchers working for
the tobacco industry, did not disclose
然而過去有些為菸草公司工作的研究者，並沒有完全揭露個人與公司之間的關係
these conflicts of interest and
try to cause doubt on this relationship.
然而過去有些為菸草公司工作的研究者，並沒有完全揭露個人與公司之間的關係
This should be prevented.
這是必須避免的利益衝究情況
You might think that people
want to practice open science,
最後來談落實開放科學的難處
why wouldn't the scientist
practice open science?
為何不是所有科學家都願意落實？
Well, one reason for
其中一個難處
this is that scientific research can
be quite a competitive enterprise.
是科學研究者之間的競爭
We see that scientists try to,
not only further scientific research, but
研究者不單是沉浸在科學研究而已
also further their own scientific careers.
他們更要拓展自己的學術生涯
And in these aspects sharing things, like
your research materials and your data,
然而，與他人分享研究材料與資料
with other people is not always
immediately to your own benefit.
並不會有立即的獲利
We can see this as a social dilemma.
這就像是兩難困境(Dawes, 1980)
If everybody would do this,
science benefits.
若大家都願意分享，則有助整體
But if I don't do it but other people
do it, I benefit more because,
但若不與他分享，則個人獲益較多
I don't have to invest anything but
I do reap the benefits.
你就像是漁翁得利裡的漁夫
So in this social dilemmas,
在這種兩難困境裡
it sometimes necessary to convince
people to practice open science.
有時開放科學的落實需要些外力
And we see that governments, who very
often found scientific research start to
像是政府補助就能奏效
acquire that researchers adhere to
open science principles more and more.
以施政鼓勵研究者們落實開放科學原則-
Now in recent years,
近幾年
this discussion is increasing because
technology makes open science possible.
因為促進開放科學的科技逐漸成熟，這樣的討論越來越多
It was very difficult to share
your research materials or
一百年前的研究者很難分享研究材料與資料
your raw data 100 years ago.
But now all the technological
challenges have been solved.
但是現在的技術難題都已經被克服
So it's possible to do this.
已無實踐的阻礙-
The question now becomes whether
you're interested in adhering
現在的問題在於研究者投入開放科學的意願
to this open science practices.
You might either do this because
you're a science funder requires
也許是研究經費補助單位的要求
you to follow open science principles and
研究者被迫分享資料，才能獲得收入等等
share all the data that was generated
by tech's money for example.
研究者被迫分享資料，才能獲得收入等等
But you can also choose to adhere
to open science principles.
但一旦你是自願遵守開放科學原則，
則讓科學本身賦予更大的意義
Because it's closely
related to the norms and
出於個人意志的行動能建立標竿
the goals that you have in doing science.
也是每位科學研究者的初衷
[MUSIC]
[課程結束]